Uh thank you for the invite. Um so I am
Victor Clarford. Uh I lead engineering
at SA where I've been for um more than
six years. So I'm one of the early
employees over there.
Um, and I'm here to uh talk to all of
you about how AI is reshaping uh
software development. So the engineering
team at SA is uh about 50 engineers.
We're um building two products, a
learning platform and an agent platform
on agents. Um so I will speak kind of
from that context about how we are
operationalizing
um being more AI enabled in in our in
how we uh build products. Um but I'll
try to talk about all of this kind of
from a general perspective uh as well.
Uh what I believe to be the the dos and
don'ts of being a software engineer uh
today and uh going into the future. And
uh for the Q&A section, I'm really
curious to sort of hear your your takes
and uh discuss this from various
perspectives. Um so what I want to cover
in this uh I believe it's 20 minutes and
then some Q&A
um is reason around this a bit on the
abstract level uh then go into a lot of
details cuz I believe we are all uh
software engineers in one shape or
another and then try to to wrap it up
and on the very abstract u level um I
think we have to start shifting our
minds a lot as software engineers if we
haven't done so
already. Um I like to say that software
engineers should think about themselves
as u agent operators and uh system
designers much more than like
programmers. Um, if the not amount if
the fraction of lines of code that you
check into git is like if the majority
is written by you and not an LLM, you
should maybe start questioning what
you're
doing.
Um, and what I mean by that is of course
like you guide it and so on. You are the
agent operator. Um but make it like
design your workflows in such a way that
the machine can do the the menial work
writing the syntax and and then
increasingly do more and more and more
and I'll go into
uh how and and what you can do to enable
the tooling to do more for you. Um, but
I want to say early on that like yes,
I'm very aware and we should all be very
aware of where do the LLM and codegen
tools perform well and where don't they.
Um, so it's I see a huge difference of
how people speak about these tools when
I talk to my friends that are like
normal front-end engineers for like
general full stack versus uh my friends
in kind of academia um where they write
code for simulations and
um maybe trying to use code to prove
some theorems these kinds of things. So
in the first context context everything
is like nice and happy and the the the
LLM can generate very relevant code but
if you're doing something fundamentally
new i.e. research the LLMs are
surprisingly bad in many cases and I
think this is an important intuition to
have and sometimes it's easy to think
that the LLMs are better at generalizing
than what they actually are. Um so like
norm a lot of normal software
engineering is in distribution of the
training data for the LLMs while if
you're doing something fundamentally new
the LLM has kind of never seen that and
uh it will be rather bad um or
relatively speaking at least. So that's
also something to guide a very important
rule of thumb when thinking about how to
use the LLMs. If you struggle to get
good results and you're like trying to
prompt it more and more and more and
more, it's going to be maybe not the
best approach. Try to figure out what's
natural for the LLM. Stay in
distribution and stay close to what um
what it has seen because they are so to
say not as good at generalizing as you
might think. It's just that the training
data is massive, right? All the text
produced by humans. So it looks like it
can generalize but maybe not so much.
And then again or like yeah what what
else the space is moving very fast so
like allow yourself to shift your
tooling much more rapidly is I think a
super important uh observation and
then this is an important point of like
the codegen tools are good in small
projects
um I think that's clear from all these
kind of um no code code gen tools out
there that that are really popular but
also in in the context of uh cursor they
struggle a lot in small code bases. So
they actually have kind of a post on
what you can do in in a larger uh
codebase. So so this is one thing to
look into and obviously like writing
these cursor uh rules is uh super super
powerful and I'll talk more about uh
that maybe before like I want to gauge
sort of where we are all at in the in
the room. How how many um regularly use
cursor or an
equivalent? Very good. How how many use
an equivalent to cursor more often than
cursor? Okay. Is that okay?
Cool. Is that like wind surf or incline
or
zed? Okay. Wind surf augment. Okay.
Continue. Very
fun.
Um and um yeah, so they talk a lot about
like n how you can structure the code
and these kinds of things. We'll get
into that, but essentially if it's easy
for a human uh to navigate, then it will
be easy for an LLM. So like it's not
like we're starting to optimize for
something that doesn't make sense for us
humans. Um but but all these
optimizations should really make sense
um for us as well because we will be
there guiding the the tooling, right?
Some some kind of code patterns that I
think are uh quite interesting is to
make the codebase have clear interfaces.
Well, obviously, but maybe this one.
Each feature should be self-contained in
a folder. Uh maybe not truism in
general, but you know this distinction
of how files are structured in a Unix
file system/bar/c,
etc. versus kind of
this.pkg folder in how you install on a
on a Mac. That's a very vague analogy,
but everything is in one place and
having collocation of code and
documentation and everything becomes
quite important. It's much easier to
specify relevant context when you're
working on a subset of of your very
large codebase. That's why I write here
to have it more be more modular and
maybe even hierarchical. So every
feature maybe has its own sort of
everything relevant to a feature is in
one folder. Imagine if you're writing
front and maybe you put your hooks and
components in different
f different folders at the root. pull
them all in close to uh the actual
feature and then you can have sort of a
a hierarchy of these meta features.
Maybe some parts of the product and
another part of the product get bundled.
Um but I still believe in in monorreos.
Um but create nice
interfaces. Um and the value of humans
becomes more and more to be like we have
the taste and the opinion. We set the
direction and the architecture. So do
express your values and opinions uh and
design patterns uh in cursor rules and
try to have that maybe even be the
source of truth for onboarding as you
introduce new engineers. Uh at SA we
usually have like someone new joins and
they're like okay where should I start?
What like how do I get on into the
codebase? I tell them to just ask cursor
in the codebase. It will of course just
read the relevant readmies and so on.
And that's actually a very good way to
figure out whether or not you have a
structure that is understandable to the
LLM. I mean you just ask it like what
what does this code do? If it can't if
it doesn't give a very like sharp
answer then you have then you maybe need
to fix your docks or structure. Um some
other interesting code patterns that are
in part counterintuitive is to have the
code base the code be much more flat.
I'll show an example on this. Um so not
over abstract and it it's we have
somewhat been trained to create
abstractions and pull everything out
into small functions and
so there's you can take that too far and
yeah I want to show a simple example in
a bit here. Um, another high level kind
of important thing that I think is
very cascade effect of us using codegen
tools is to enable everyone to work
outside their area of of expertise. Um,
essentially have everyone become
fullstack engineers
um to some extent at least. So front-
end experts should be able to write UI
updates. Um I think this is a thing that
distinguishes really productive teams
from less productive teams today and
especially uh going into the future. Um
if you are in this situation where like
you're a back end engineer and you kind
of cannot touch the front end you need
to sync with some other team sync with
their road map all of this you know
you're just like you get stuck
everything was really uh slow.
Yeah, most engineers are are full stack.
Um, but I appreciate that you you
challenge me challenging me on this
because there's a nuance of course. For
example, our backend infrastructure
engineers, they are like so far detached
from the front end that they rarely have
a reason to to touch it perhaps. and the
people on the very other side of the
spectrum working more closely with with
design like the pixel perfect touch and
feel UI
implementation they won't be touching
the schema migrations you're asking
because I see the value of it
see I got for loving cars
to it means yes and um a reason for this
is actually I can share so we have two
products right uh the first one is
cotlin on the back end and typescript
react on the front end uh when we
introduced our second product on agents
um we decided to write that uh fully in
typescript so typescript full stack
we're using tRPC as the full stack or
the front and back end communication
layer so you usually easily share types
and
everything that was very intentional of
this like especially at the at the
startup or when you need to iterate
quickly. You want to enable everyone to
work end to end. Imagine one person
being able to set the database schema
and use those types and everything all
the way out to the front end. When you
can hold the code so to say in in in
your hands, you can be so much more
productive than if you have this like
syncs and road maps and
But there's nuances to this to to what
extent you can you can make it uh work.
And today what what's really cool is if
cursor is I think if I'm simplifying
like best at just like front end
implementation it's localized and it
doesn't have state like a database. So
people that work more on the back end
and ah now we added this type it needs
to be visible in the form. these things
are now like cursor just does it for
them. I think that's a huge
enabler.
So this can be fun to talk a bit about.
I personally think cursor is on average
like best right now but there are so
many alternatives and everything is
shifting. So, it's very fun to hear
people using quite a wide range of of
tooling here and um MCP's all all the
the rage now somehow. So, I think I want
to spend just a minute on that. And um I
saw just recently Open AAI
uh added MCP support to their response
API
uh also. So you can just hook up an MCP
server and it becomes available for the
um in in in the API then. But MCP on
some level is just a
um badly implemented uh API. Badly
implemented in the sense that is usually
it's just standard input output. Most of
the MCP servers is great if it's like
you're running a single user on one
computer. Sure, but you can't really use
them in a production setting.
um there are these sec alternatives and
and so but it's a great concept because
it just standardizes how we can expose
tools to in this case a cursor and it
doesn't matter that they are not
scalable the implementations. So I want
to highlight some interesting
um examples. So this is what we have
oops um checked in but people are
playing with a bunch of different uh
things. This one, browser tools, is
quite fun if you're
um if you're working with kind of front-
end development. So, this allows your um
cursor agent to have access to your
running browser. So, you can ask it to
to it knows the um it knows what
elements you have focused in the
debugger. Um it sees the network errors,
it sees the console outputs. Um, so a
powerful iteration loop is of course
when you have it just see lint errors
and stuff and it just runs with this. It
can also see actual runtime errors in
the browser. Um, other nice MCP
uh servers that you can hook up to
cursor I think like if you're working
with GCP and managing a lot of resources
um the GCP MCP is pretty nice etc. Um,
right. I want to
say I think we're all in this room. Of
course, having this enabled, so I think
we should all be leaning into having
these
um tools do as much as possible for us
run automatically
um and rely a lot on static tests like
lint rules and good types and and so on
because it does pick up on all of this
in the ID. Uh maybe you click some of
these boxes depending on your level of
paranoia. But
um uh fun fun thing I don't know if
everyone knows but cursor is
um currently ah back yeah background
agents. So why I'm like okay you can
already have it run agent style
um in the ID but cursor
is currently preview releasing and soon
it will go into general availability uh
background the agents so they will spin
up an ID in the
cloud and you can just yeah spin it up
and when I talk to to the folks over
there a lot of them are actually
internally running with the 03 um model
which is a thinking model and very slow,
right? But they give it rather heavy
tasks and then you don't want to sit
there and wait for it or have like five
cursor windows open at the same time.
So, so they are now going in the
direction of kind of what Devon was
doing originally. But I think cursor is
very um strategical in how they're
navigating the space first being where
we are as engineers and then
increasingly just
um yeah automating it, having it run in
the background. So this I think will be
a really interesting shift. Are we like
are we ready for it? Is the tooling
ready for it? Are the LLM's competent
enough maybe soonish. So the timing here
is quite interesting. And I think the
reason that the fact that they are
introducing it now is an indication that
they believe um the LLM are starting to
get stable enough for that kind of use
case.
Yeah, I was one quick mention like
cursor rules very powerful and
especially if in a large code base you
can sort of set the scopes and and so on
and guide it but I think still automatic
checks like types and lengths are to be
preferred somehow they are strict you
have guarantees they're also they show
up for humans The more you can rely on
this, the the better. But some some
patterns of course need to be expressed
more vaguely in in natural
text. So let's jump to some uh some code
uh examples or or patterns. I hinted to
this like flat code is good. I want to
show explicitly what I mean.
Um yeah, let's maybe look at the example
first. This is a bit of like contrived
example of course but uh I I said this
thing you know we've been kind of taught
to pull out
um everything into small functions like
get username first name space last name
um but if you do this a lot and like put
them in different files and you think
you're yes I'm doing the right thing it
gets very messy uh complex difficult to
navigate for both humans and and LLMs um
so just like inline stuff if it's rather
simple
this is so much easier to to to read
even for humans.
Um, and I think this becomes more
important
um now as we have LMS generate and read
code for us because they they lack
context so much. So if these are in
different in other files and you just
see this like what what's actually
happening um it's not
um clear and then they need to do like
lookups in that those files everything
becomes really slow somehow and it maybe
ties back into this idea of uh um lean
into the natural tendencies of the LLMs
on for good and bad I don't know but I
think we all have made the observation
that they prefer to write very flat code
like if you're reusing the same
component a couple of times, it happily
reimplements it so to say or writes out
the class names or
whatever. Um, is that good? Is it not
good? Um, there's a balance to to this
of course.
Um, so a bit less composition I see in
our codebase and and others is to be a
somewhat common pattern.
um make the code like easy to read
linearly from top to bottom and without
jumping through through many um many
files. Uh and maybe another reason for
why sort of abstractions become a bit
less important is perhaps that
um code will be reused I think
less in the future and just rewritten
all the time because it's cheap, it's
fast, it
just that seems to be the natural
tendency of the LLMs.
Um and uh as we as engineers transition
from being the programmers to the agent
orchestrators, so much more code will be
written. Um and I think the demand for
code as a consequence of that will
increase. So um our jobs as programmers
will for sure be replaced. Someone but
someone needs
to coach or operate the the future
programmers i.e. the LLMs and the demand
for this role is going to be very high.
Everyone will want hundred times as many
lines of code produced. So we'll have uh
different kinds of of headaches as
engineers. Um the other example, final
example, final slide.
Um this the front end team uh uh was is
now in the transition of switching we
were using style components to to
tailwind.
Um yeah, I'll make the comparison very
uh simple here. Um everything becomes
more concise, but most importantly
things become inlined again. Flat collo
kit. So the card component up here is
used down here. It's nice in some way.
You have it semantic name for it and so
on. But here the the usage and the
declaration of it is like inlined.
Everything is collocated.
Um, this seems to be much easier for
LLMs to to deal with. Yes.
Ah, how do you ensure that the styles
make are synchronized across? Yes, very
good question. Two approaches to that.
Um, strict you can actually have we have
lint rules on what classes are allowed
and not. So, that's cool. You have
static guarantees.
um you want to maybe disallow a bunch of
weird colors and stuff and you maybe
want to kind of enforce usage of of your
own custom classes. That's one example.
The other is to express your design
philosophy in cursor
rules. So a mix of
static Yeah, exactly. And of course
maybe the card in a real world scenario
maybe the card component would actually
be a component that exists that is
reused. So with that I want to conclude
and and and sum up the sort of
observations and what I believe to be
the dos and don'ts in this context. Um
colllocate files modularize create a
nice hierarchical structure in your
monor repo. write increasingly flat code
with maybe less composition in the sense
of like less jumping to this file, this
file, this file and somewhere you have
some root
component. Um, codify your architectural
decisions or system design preferences.
So we humans will increasingly be the
ones contributing with a taste. What
does good look like? Um, and then have
the
LLM run with it.
uh en enable everyone to work outside of
their area of expertise.
everyone becomes the full stack to some
extent or like we want to move in that
direction and and give all your devs
very easy access to to good uh tooling.
Um I was surprised but when I and when
we enabled like cursor um the business
plan so that everyone just signs in and
they don't have to expense it themselves
a bit more engineers started using it
but like help everyone just lower the
bars. um to to
adopt all the all this new tech and be
like really really quick explore try try
different stuff I think that's where a
lot of your edge as an engineer will be
in having the competence of how to how
to navigate and orchestrate all the
tooling that exists thank
you and now we have time for our
questions great great talk and I'm
definitely all aboard with what you're
saying about agent offering S um I just
want to push maybe a little bit like
what what is the next step suggestion
another word that's thrown around a lot
is everybody becomes a manager. Mhm. So
maybe agent manager is the next step. So
I had this uh sort of revelation this
morning when I tried out the new release
from Google uh Google AI yesterday. Uh
was it called Judas where which is more
like de or codeex? Yes. Uh and probably
also like the background agent uh I'd be
curious to hear what you have to say
about it. I just fired up a task this
morning to my code base to give me a
solid read for a relatively competitive
repo and it came back a few minutes
later with with a solved task and I get
five tasks a day and to me it's like I
have like a junior developer half time
with me for that time or maybe
so I become more of a manager to that
agent. I just have to structure the
tasks very well. Yes. And have it do it
uh and their own which is totally
different from the cursor paradigm where
you're always pressed.
Any insight any revelations from from
the background agent mode or something
you want to share about that? I I think
this this is a great point you're you're
raising there of um we see many of the
big labs and so on now releasing this um
more autonomous coding agents um and
cursor like they're all doing it at the
same time. That's an indication that
this is starting to work. Devon I think
it was more than or yeah a year ago or
so when they launched it everyone got so
excited and then uh once people started
getting um their hands on it it's like
oh aha okay maybe not so fun after all.
Um increasingly of course they will be
very autonomous and and do a lot for us.
Um and again it depends on where you
are. Are you doing something
fundamentally new out of distribution?
maybe you need to be closer holding
their hand. Uh if it's just iterating on
UI bugs or data plumbing between the
front end and the back end, uh the
autonomous approach will probably be
very powerful very soon. And I think
you're saying something important with
your job, our job becomes to uh be
explicit and correct in defining the
problem.
It's like if I I studied math and or
like if you studied anything analytical,
you probably have this intuition with
you that half or more of solving the
problem is formulating the problem.
Well, um it's kind of similar
here what people say.
Thank you. Very nice talk. Uh I thought
you on the direction where we're going.
Uh however I'm I'm thinking about
specifically this flat code you
that's kind of reducive is it
reusability
and you said also that more and more
codes the weak them is it instead of
reuse uh I'm thinking about some from
the perspective of the viewer of the
code how do you deal with that because
there's more method which is re yeah
written yes you deal with that with the
code reviews uh great questions I want
want to say two things on that. Uh one
thing is depending on how ambitious you
are as you look into the future I think
one perspective is that there will not
really be s software as today there will
be databases and APIs and there will be
generated UIs custommade for every
individual or every department and every
team. I think an example is uh every
sales team I ever ever sort of
interacted with, they all hate the their
CRM system. Uh but the basic data is
very um um the data is very basic. So I
mean let's them let them just have their
generated UI on top of a fundamental
database. I think we'll see that much
more.
Um and and that UI basically I mean in
the very long run maybe it's generated
on the fly almost uh intermediate step
is it's someone somewhat technical
generates it once for the specific use
case and then the team uses it um and
how okay the other part is what what
what to do with the with reviews
uh one thing is to say have an LLM do
the reviewing
Uh and um deal with it like two of you
sir. Yeah. I so at at SA we we sell to
large enterprises. So we have um sock
and ISO certifications that we need to
to adhere to which basically mandates us
to do very strict reviews on everything.
We're also a company that want to move
really fast and like I'm of the opinion
why why should some another human look
at the code if a senior competent
competent engineer feels like this is an
obvious fix no one needs to spend the
time looking at it so we we remain
compliant with everything by having the
person that checks in the code specify a
sort of risk level on the change and if
it's low risk uh we have an LLM
reviewer
yes sorry
Hi. Uh yeah, you briefly mentioned mo
and Mhm. But I was wondering if you've
made like uh other architectural
decisions to support LLM like going for
microservices that have a smaller
context so the LLM can understand it or
an easily replaceable microser like if
you want to if are you making those kind
of decision LLM coding is I think um
yeah one such decision was to use um
TypeScript file stack and TRPC so we
have the types propagate all the way um
I'm personally not a huge fan of uh of
microservices
um uh because I'm mostly operating in a
context where we want to have engineers
be able to make end-to-end changes
rather quickly. If an end toend change
involves deploying one two three
microservices
uh you intro you are introducing
barriers for yourself. Um, another way
to look at microservices is that like
not always but sometimes in many cases
people want to have them so that they
have nice
um separation of
concerns. It's just code. If you want to
have separation of concerns, go ahead
and do it in in one service. Uh, I think
that should be this first step. Uh, and
if you feel like, oh, but I can't be
disciplined enough. I need a separate
service. I mean sometimes you hear this
argument ah but it will be messy we need
to separate it into a separate
service then then you I think the
problem is uh somewhere else and but but
creating the modularization just do it
in the codebase you can pretend it's a
different service you can pretend it's
started from somewhere else and then you
have like 90% of the games without the
the pain of separate deployments I'm
simplifying a lot so we can we can chat
more about
Okay. Uh so uh um thank you for this
talk. Uh you you talk about using LLMs a
lot. Uh and that kind of rises the
question of um LLMs are not
stakeholders. So should we be concerned
about the origin of these LLMs or about
the complexity that we assigned?
Yes. Are your thoughts about
that?
Um so one thing is yeah codify what what
what matters in in documentation and
cursor rules and so but you can't always
trust that they will adhere to this. I I
guess in in a sense you answer this
because you have a review process where
you have two different coders that need
to understand the code and review it
before it goes in. So that kind of tells
me that you are aware that it needs to
be reviewed by a human. Oh yeah. But
what about the origin? Would you be uh
okay by using a Chinese model for
example uh like deepseek?
I would be less okay with it if it's
just supposed to write CSS. I think
Chinese CSS is very similar to my
American CSS.
Uh but um more generally I think uh the
the true answer to this question is
precisely as um like to what extent will
we trust LLM? It's exactly the same as
to what extent will we trust
humans. This my first interaction with
someone I will be kind of skeptical like
oh they give me some artifact. What is
this? Can I trust it? But if we've done
it that dance back and forth I say
something, you say something and like
everything you say makes sense. After
some time I don't even have to check it.
I will just trust you. I think it's the
same with the LLMs. And then yeah, if
you trust too much, you will get um
burnt. But but that fundamental aspect
is is there right? You you trust your
very senior uh backend engineer to go
into the production database. Yeah.
I don't think you trust them because
they are humans. I think I think you
trust them because of the consistency in
the interaction. It's like a game
theoretic thing going on. You're playing
a game
um with this human and you you the the
incentives are are aligned and so on. I
just want to say this is very
interesting. There's infinitely many
nuances to this as you know when when
you stand here and say things you have
to simplify and I'm aware I'm doing it.
So let's talk more. Yeah. Uh nice
presentation. I have a question
regarding I mean you talk talked about
generating new code uh right but we have
existing code which works in production
and we as developer are always quite you
know uh thinking about we shouldn't
change it and all that. How do you
approach that and how do you verify the
code you are generating on a big level
and obviously it will grow with time?
Yeah. So what's the verification process
of it that it works? Are you doing some
testing or what? Yeah, super good
question and I I want to make first a
kind of distinction between two classes
of of development. One is when you have
a really robust system in production,
lots of users, it's creating a lot of
business value, everything like it's
kind of static. you want to maintain it
and maybe do small small incremental
changes. The other context is like small
startup moving really fast changing
everything every day. Um I've have in
this conversation been talking a bit
more from this perspective. So it's good
that you raised this this point of like
how do you work well when like the
stakes are super high and everything
needs to be really really really like
tight and robust and this is in a
context you will have a lot more tests
in place and I think a fun thing here I
I wrote it but didn't really voice it
over but testdriven development with
agents um is is really powerful um you
have your tests in place you and maybe
you want to make a change so you you
change the tests And then you can step
back and start the cursor agent or
whatever LLM agent you have it. Give it
access to running the tests. Give it
access to changing the codebase. Make it
loop until the tests pass. I think
that's a pretty cool um way to work with
it. But of course, if the context is
really high stakes, you need to sit
there and verify the results or you ask
them to write test for you. Well, yes. I
either you write the test or they write
the test or maybe you have them you back
coming back to this it's all about the
problem formulation you define very
clearly what's the scope what's what's
the problem or the solution then have it
write the tests check that the tests
make sense then have it write the
implementation
thank you
thanks oh no it works uh yeah thank you
Victor and uh we need to take A short
break. This is fun. Yes. Few minutes.